Inventory of the Dorsey-Coupland Papers 1840-1876, 1843-1865
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Letters, 1840-1866, n.d., 174 items. (Box-folder 1:1-4)
  - A. Sidney Robertson, Iberville, [Louisiana ], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 18 January 1854., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Received her letter and will remit a draft to her in the amount of $183; had previously received a letter from Carter [Coupland] giving the amount he [ASR] owed her in error; responded to Carter's letter and informed him that he [ASR] owes her $225.04; will send balance with the interest she desires in a short time; has had a good sugar crop this year and sent some to Louisville in the hope that he can get a better price there than in New Orleans; discusses the worth of one of her slaves and mentions the loss of one of his; has made up a barrel of syrup just for her; wishes John [Coupland] had purchased the plantation he [ASR] had suggested as the value has increased dramatically.
  - John H. Marshall, Mobile, [Alabama], to Juliana Dorsey, n.p., 3 Feb[ruar]y 1854., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Sends information on the account she holds with Marshall & Son; holds twenty shares of Mobile Insurance Company for her; asks for the note he gave her as he has no record of it in his books; sends his love.
    Bears ALS from John H. Marshall, Mobile, [Alabama], to Juliana Dorsey, n.p. Shows the information relating to her account with Marshall & Son. 1 p.
  - George Conway, Mobile, [Alabama], to J[uliana] Dorsey, Petersburg, Virginia, 1 August 1854., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Would have collected and forwarded the amount owed her but it was difficult to collect at this time of year; is "under the necessity of omitting $50 in the am[oun]t due by D. Walkin for Nelson"; encloses a check for $420.50 and hopes it is enough to meet her purposes.
  - John [R. Coupland], Stony Point, [Albermarle County, Virginia], to Mrs. John R. Coupland, Red Sunset Springs, Alleghany County, Virginia, 14 Sept[ember] 1854., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Speaks of the love he has for his dear wife; knows that she loves him as well, even though she says she has not the language to express it; wishes that he would never have to be apart from her; has sold the carriage for $350 and will use the money to buy a piano in Richmond.
  - Thomas Branch & Sons, Petersburg, [Virginia], to J[uliana] Dorsey, n.p., 8 Nov[ember] 1854., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Urges her to accept Mr. Harrison as security as he is now good for $20,000; gives details for the sale of her land.
  - Jno. [John] H. Marshall, Mobile, [Alabama], to Juliana Dorsey, n.p., 29 Nov[ember] 1854., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Encloses a check for $1199.34; hopes the check reaches her in time; Mr. Collins is to be married this evening to Miss Gale.
  - George Conway, Mobile, [Alabama], to Juliana Dorsey, Petersburg, Virginia, 16 December 1854., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Encloses a check for $200; mentions that "the negroes are well excepting Becky, who has been complaining for several days."
  - Jno. [John] H. [Marshall], Mobile, [Alabama], to Juliana [Dorsey], n.p. 11 Jan[uar]y 1855., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Encloses a check for $119.10; discusses other monetary matters; Mollie has been sick but can now come down to her meals.
  - George Conway, Mobile, [Alabama], to Juliana Dorsey, Yorktown, Virginia, 10 February 1855., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Encloses a check for $230 for negro hire; attempted to obtain the $200 from Dr. Ketchum but was told it was impossible at this time; gathered up all he could and is forwarding this amount to her as asked.
  - Thomas Branch & Sons, Petersburg, [Virginia], to Juliana Dorsey, Yorktown, Virginia, 21 Feb[ruar]y 1855., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Regrets the inconveniences she has experienced with the sale of her land; Mr. Flower has not yet arrived but assures her that he is honest; has paid Mr. Davis for the negro hire.
  - Tho[ma]s W. Upshur, Norfolk, [Virginia], to Mattie Pierce, Williamsburgh [sic], Virginia, 1 August 1855., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Asks for a correspondence with her; was very surprised to find she left so quickly this morning without allowing him a chance to say goodbye.
  - Tho[ma]s W. Upshur, Oakland, to Mattie [Pierce], n.p., 7 August 1855., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Is quite glad that she did not refuse a correspondence with him; people are leaving Norfolk "by the boatloads yet still there is no real cause of alarm"; there has been no new case of fever for two days and the sick have been moved out to Oak Grove hospital where not one has died; the streets are deserted and few were in church on Sunday; has something to tell her that he would rather tell her in person; wishes that they are to meet again.
  - W[illia]m G. Dunbar, Norfolk, [Virginia], to Mattie [Pierce], n.p. 1 Dec[ember] 1855., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Regrets that he cannot accept the invitation to be present at Mrs. Henley's next week.
  - Tho[ma]s W. Upshur, n.p., to Mattie [Pierce], n.p., 16 December 1855., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Was unable to attend Mrs. Henley's party earlier this month; hopes to continue the correspondence if it is agreeable to her.
  - [Juliana Dorsey], Glebe, to her son Carter [Coupland], n.p., 20 Dec[embe]r 1855., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Shares family news; encloses Alf's note for what he owes and asks that a check for it be sent to her; wants $1880 and hopes she can raise it.
  - [Juliana Dorsey], Williamsburg, [Virginia], to [Carter Coupland], n.p., 25 Jan[uar]y 1856., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Feels that it is almost useless to try to mail a letter as the rivers are frozen and the roads are impassable; has not suffered from the cold but hasn't stirred from her warm room; would like to buy 50 acres and build a small cottage in which to live; asks that he remit the payment directly that he receives from Mr. Conway, Alf, and John Marshall.
  - W.L. Watkins, Petersburg, [Virginia], to Juliana Dorsey, Evergreen, Prince George [County], Virginia, 21 April 1856., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Informs her that a brother of Mr. Flowers[?] has arrived to prevent his property from being sold; asks that she send all the bonds she holds against Mr. Flowers so that he [WLW] can perfect the arrangement.
    Including ALS from W.L. Watkins, Petersburg, [Virginia], to Juliana Dorsey, Evergreen, Prince George [County], Virginia, describing her statement of account with him. 1 p.
  - J[uliana] Dorsey, Evergreen, to Carter [Coupland], n.p., 10 May 1856., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Gives details of a land transaction that he is to handle for her.
  - J[uliana] D[orsey], Petersburg, [Virginia], to Carter [Coupland], n.p., 26 May 1856., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Encloses duplicate checks, but hopes the first reached him safely; will sign the contract to buy their land tomorrow and will stay with Mrs. Henley for two or three weeks; John's house is almost done, except for the doors and windows.
  - J[uliana] D[orsey], Williamsburg, [Virginia], to Carter [Coupland], n.p., 3 June 1856., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Has concluded the land deal fairly amicably; discusses business matters; John [R. Coupland]'s house will be habitable in four or five weeks; expects to be able to pay off her house in two or three years and then will have a nice income from it.
  - E. Ruffin, Jr., Beechwood, to his aunt J[uliana] Dorsey, Petersburg, Virginia, 14 Aug[ust] 1856., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Discusses business matters.
  - J[uliana] D[orsey], n.p., to Carter [Coupland], n.p., 17 Aug[ust] 1856., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Asks him to attend to her business matters immediately; needs a note for $1000 to settle the business between her and Edmund Ruffin; asks about his activities.
  - George A. Ketchum, Mobile, [Alabama], to Carter [Coupland], n.p., 19 Aug[ust] 1856., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Informs him that when the servant Neill [?] was told he was to be sent to Virginia, he became upset at the idea of leaving his young wife and children; asks if he could buy Neill so the family could stay together; needs to buy Neill on time as he has not the cash to outlay right now; mentions that Neill has had syphilis several times and is not entirely sound; wonders if he would make a trade for him.
  - E. Ruffin, Jr., Beechwood, to "Aunt" [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 4 Sept[ember] 1856., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Discusses business matters and shares family news.
  - Wilmer A. Jones, n.p. to Carter [Coupland], n.p., 16 July 1857., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Asks for the amount owed to him for the sale of a cart to him [CC]; has a debt to pay off and does not quite have all the money needed for it.
  - W. L. Watkins, at Petersburg, [Virginia], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 31 July 1857., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Reassures her that any check that Mr. Mann writes is good; explains that he has not written because he has been expecting to find out whether Mr. Wright, a previous owner of her land, has paid the taxes on it; assures her not to worry as someone did pay the taxes, according to the City Collector.
    Bears ALS from John Mann, Petersburg, [Virginia], to Julianna [sic] Dorsey, n.p., 31 July 1857. Describes the statement of Mr. Tho[ma]s B. Flower's bond to her in the amount of $423.10; is enclosing a check for that amount; asks that she send a receipt for it at her earliest convenience as he wishes to send it to Mr. Flower before he [JM] leaves for the mountains. 1 p. ALS.
    Bears ALS from John Mann, Petersburg, [Virginia], to Julianna [sic] Dorsey, n.p., 31 July 1857. Statement of account of Juliana Dorsey with Thomas B. Flower. ALS.
  - Jno. [John] Leyburn, Philadelphia, [Penn.], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 3 Aug[us]t 1857., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Regrets to inform her he must decline her call to form a Presbyterian church in Williamsburg; at present he desires to remain in Philadelphia; mentions the difficulty in establishing a church in Williamsburg and instead suggests that she ask a local presbytery to send someone to preach; the five dollars she sent arrived safely and he will send a receipt as soon as he can.
  - E. Ruffin, Jr., Beechwood, to Juliana [Dorsey], n.p., 4 May 1859., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Received her draft for $300 and the statement of the deposit of $150 in credit; will go to Petersburg in a few days to draw the money and credit; describes Father's bruised hand which has given him great pain for many days; Mrs. L. seems well again and he hopes that she escapes her spring attack of neuralgia this year; all at the Glebe and at Julian's are well; asks when she will come visit as John [R. Coupland] and his wife can take care of the farm and house while she is gone.
  - E. Ruffin, Jr., Beechwood, to Juliana [Dorsey], n.p., 1 June 1859., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Explains his cashing of the draft she sent him; has no more houseguests as they have all left; asks if she can come up to fill their places.
  - J.Y. Russell, Petersburg, [Virginia] to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 14 Sept[ember] 1859., ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Discusses his cotton crop; informs her that he cannot pay as yet the $1500 he promised John R. Coupland for "value received" and encloses a note for that amount.
    Bears ALS from J.Y. Russell, Petersburg, [Virginia] to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 16 Sept[ember] 1859. Note of promise to pay John R. Coupland in the amount of $1500. 1 p.
  - J.Y. Russell, Petersburg, to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 29 Sept[ember] 1859., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Explains that "money (what the merchants sometimes call) is 'tight'" and cannot pay off the note as yet; is sure that he will be able to pay it off if it were extended another four months; sends check for $979; discusses cotton prices.
  - John [R. Coupland], Willoughby, to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 14 Nov[ember] 1859., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Will attempt to get all done that she wishes him to do; Charles has been sick with the chills for several days and so he [JRC] has been very busy in the fields; mentions the arrival of Mr. Buck; writes chiefly to tell her that Mr. Coke's contract is out; mentions there is no hack from Allen's Wharf at King's Mill; will go down to meet Cousin Leward when she goes to the Grove or else will send Miles; sends his love.
  - J.Y. Russell, at Petersburg, to [Juliana Dorsey], 18 November 1859., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Advises her to take the 100 bales of cotton; informs her that she should have taken his offer for $1500; has received a letter from Mobile that she must pay taxes and doctors' bills for her men.
  - Carter [Coupland], aboard Steamer Dalman, to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 1 Jan[uar]y 1860., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Has some time to write to her now that he is finished with his duties for the night and the passengers have retired; spent Christmas dinner with John Marshall and enjoyed it immensely; mentions that Mollie is looking thin, but is still cheerful; explains that "old Rheumatism has got me still; I can manage to creep about, but suffer a great deal"; hopes that the rheumatism stays in his legs because if it moves up to his arms "the thing will be out with me and no mistake."
  - J.Y. Russell, Petersburg, [Virginia] to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 18 Jan[uary] 1860., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Explains that his last letter was to inform her that the board will let her pay $300 to $500 and extend the balance to the first of June; sends a note to be signed by her and endorsed by John R. Coupland.
    Bears ALS from J.Y. Russell, James City County, Virginia, to [Juliana Dorsey], 18 Jan[uar]y 1860. A blank note addressed to John R. Coupland to pay for value received. 1 p.
  - J.Y. Russell, Petersburg, [Virginia] to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 25 Jan[uary] 1860., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Received her check for $389.96 for curtailment of her note of $1000; has paid that amount on the old note and filled up the new note for $626.29 for next June 1st; encloses the pen he bought; expects to go to Mobile in the spring but is still unsure of the exact time.
  - H. Emory, Suffolk, Nansemond County, Virginia, to [Juliana] Dorsey, n.p., 28 Jan[uar]y 1860., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Suggests that she pay the amount due him to his brother.
    Bears ALS from H. Emory, Suffolk, Nansemond County, Virginia, to his brother, [?], 28 Jan[uar]y 1860. Fears that his last letter was miscarried; asks him to write soon. 1 p. ALS.
  - John [R. Coupland], Galveston, to [Mrs. John R. Coupland], n.p., 1 April 1860., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Describes his passage across the Gulph [sic]; tells her he misses her greatly and is suffering from loneliness at having to be separated from his loved ones; asks if there is sickness at home because "something I know is the matter" as she has not yet written; will travel soon to Indianola and then on to Goliad, where Judge Hughes lives; fears that he "shall make nothing out of the Judge" because though he has money, others say he is always "hard up"; describes Galveston and the high price of land; tells her to expect him on the 25th; asks her to send a boat for him to Jamestown, theirs if it is fixed, otherwise Mrs. Jones'; asks her to write him at Richmond.
  - J.Y. Russell, Petersburg, [Virginia], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 17 May 1860., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Has arranged that she should only have to pay $200 and the balance will be extended four months; asks that she sign the note, have it endorsed, and send it and the $200 to him; is not yet sure of the amount of the note, so would like her to leave the date and the amount blank for him to fill in; asks that she leave him alone when it comes to cotton; sends the $500 canceled note and encloses one for $600 that he may use.
  - J.Y. Russell, Petersburg,, [Virginia] to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 17 July 1860., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Has paid the $200 she sent on the note, which leaves a balance of $430.43; has not yet used the $600 note she sent; informs her that the cotton operations have lost much more than the $1000 she put into his hands and tells her that she should therefore keep quiet about it to him until he says something to her.
    Enclosure: note for $626.29 from Juliana Dorsey to John R. Coupland.
  - Selden and Miller, Richmond, [Virginia], to Jno. [John] R. Coupland, n.p., 5 Oct[ober] 1860., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Has sold his wheat for a total of $997.17, half cash and half four months' note; sends him the cash and has discounted the note; feels the sale a good one and hopes he finds it satisfactory.
  - J[ohn] H. Marshall, Mobile, [Alabama], to Juliana [Dorsey], n.p., 3 Dec[ember] 1860., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Has waited for the receipt of the $100 from J.W. Mann in order to write; mentions that "money matters here are in a terrible fix, no one paying anything that can possibly help it"; Anna M. has been quite sick and one of their negroes is in the bedroom and hourly expected to die; everyone is getting better and expected to pull through; informs her that their church is full and has a popular preacher; Geo[rge] W. Tarleton took Communion the day before; Charles Hopkins is either dead or dying.
  - Charles Lively, n.p., to John R. Coupland, n.p., 1860., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Has sent the goods ashore for his mother; could not get the salt for there was none to be found in Richmond; put the money for the wheat in the bank.
  - R. R. Banks, Petersburg, [Virginia], to Juliana Dorsey, Williamsburg, Virginia, 2 Jan[uar]y 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Received the turkeys she sent and sold them all; asks how many she sent so that he can reimburse her for the ones that did not make it; sends a check for $26.05; thanks her for her "sympathy in these hard times that are trying the souls of our best men."
  - J.Y. Russell, Petersburg, [Virginia], to Juliana Dorsey, Williamsburg, Virginia, 11 Jan[uary] 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Informs her that their friend Mr. W[illia]m Sayre is dead; paid the note with the $100 she sent.
  - J.Y. Russell, Petersburg, [Virginia], to Juliana Dorsey, near Williamsburg, Virginia, 27 Feb[ruary] 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Encloses the old note for $400; the new note is filled up for $150 less the $4.19 he owes her; informs her that the balance of $145.81 is due 6 June 1861.
  - Smyth, Stone, and Banks, Petersburg, [Virginia], to Juliana Dorsey, at Williamsburg, Virginia, 30 March 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Informs her that she can pay the balance of the bill at her convenience.
  - Cha[rle]s L. C. Dupuy, New Orleans, [Louisiana ], to Juliana Dorsey, Williamsburg, [Virginia], 18 May 1861., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Writes to inform her that the Battalion of Washington Artillery, of which he is a member, has been accepted into service for the President of the Confederate States for the war; will leave next Thursday equipped with six six-pound guns and two twelve-pound howitzers, along with ammunition.
  - Henri W. Perrin, at Camp De Soto, Virginia, to Mattie Pierce, Williamsburg, Virginia, 13 Sept[ember] 1861., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Informs her that his haversack is missing and prevails upon her to make him another; had a severe chill on Wednesday but feels well this morning; mentions that Camp De Soto is a very lonesome place and hopes that he will soon be stationed near Williamsburg; sends his regards.
  - Henri W. Perrin, at Pelican Camp, Virginia, to Mattie Pierce, Williamsburg, Virginia, 6 Nov[ember] 1861., 9 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Describes the death of a past lover of his caused by a strange man he met in Spain, and his feud with him ending in a duel that caused the man to lose his right arm; asks her if he is still worthy to be her friend; feels that he is not the kind of man she would want to associate with because of this feud that has controlled his past.
  - A.M. Dupuy, Richmond, [Virginia], to [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 18 Nov[ember] 1861., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Informs her that Brother George has arrived, but as a fugitive from Lincoln's troops, who have "proscribed him as an Arch Traitor"; mentions that his wedding has been put off because his bride could find no wedding finery as "nothing could be got be obtained now in Eddyville"; informs her that George was robbed of $550 in gold on his way to Virginia; reassures her that the check for $25 came safely; will send her $10 when she is able to build her church; the price of burning fluid is up to $2.25 per gallon.
  - H[enri] W. Perrin, Williamsburg, Virginia, to Mattie Pierce, Williamsburg, Virginia, 21 Nov[ember] 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Sends regrets that he cannot go on the ride planned for this morning due to a severe chill he received after their walk this morning; will call tomorrow if possible.
  - Carter [Coupland], aboard Steamer Beulah, to Mother, Juliana Dorsey, Williamsburg, Virginia, 23 Nov[ember] 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Had a rather unpleasant trip to Montgomery, [Alabama] as he was put in the car with sick soldiers; feels better after having had a bath and put on clean clothes; informs her that his cold is better.
  - T. Witherspoon, Greensboro, to Aunt [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 4 Dec[ember] 1861., 10 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Grieves for her [TW] husband's death on the first of December after a lingering illness; gives details of his decline; shares her unhappiness and her uncertainty about the future.
  - Exchange Bank of Virginia, Petersburg, [Virginia], to Juliana Dorsey, n.p., 10 Feb[ruar]y 1862., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Has received the bank notes and checks amounting to $200; has placed the amount to the credit of Capt. Edmund Ruffin, Jr.
  - T. Witherspoon, Greensboro, to Aunt [Juliana Dorsey], n.p., 24 Feb[ruary] 1862., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Describes the "desperate sickening desolation of widowhood with its pressure and responsibilities"; finds her consolation in God; mentions that she is "very well, considering my recent confinement -- my baby being just four weeks old"; describes her baby as being sixteen pounds, two ounces with red hair and blue eyes; has named the baby William, her "dear Alfred's first name"; informs her that Mobile is expecting an attack, and families are leaving and sending away their valuables; another company is forming in her town; her household now numbers twenty-eight with her mother's servants who had no other refuge.
  - W. R. Chew, Clifton, Louisiana, to Juliana Dorsey, n.p. 5 Ap[ri]l 1862., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Bears the sad news that their mutual friend A. Sidney Robertson's daughter died when the bank on which she was standing gave way and she drowned; her body has yet to be recovered; assures her that her last letter to Robertson was received, and he will reply in person "so soon as he can compose himself sufficiently to do so."
  - Sister of Edm. Ruffin [Jane S. Dupuy], at Windrow, to Mary [?], 4 March 1863., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Reassures her that she is thought of on a daily basis; apologizes for her long neglect, which resulted from her [JSD] giving up her room to houseguests, and also to the fact that she could not procure any stamps for a period of weeks; shares news of family and friends; mentions that Lottie is "quite alone in the County [Prince George] all the residents having fled to Petersburg many of whom have died"; describes the many cases of diphtheria in her area; Freeman returned from college with scarlet fever; mentions an outbreak of smallpox but due to the vaccinations there have been no deaths; returns again to the subject of family and friends.